<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">

<bookinfo>
<title>DVD-o-matic</title>
<author><firstname>Carl</firstname><surname>Hetherington</surname></author>
</bookinfo>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Hello, and welcome to DVD-o-matic!
</para>

<section>
<title>What is DVD-o-matic?</title>

<para>
DVD-o-matic is a program to generate <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Cinema_Package">Digital
Cinema Packages</ulink> (DCPs) from DVDs, Blu-Rays, video files such as MP4
and AVI, or still images.  The resulting DCPs will play on modern digital
cinema projectors.
</para>

<para>
You might find it useful to make DVDs easier to present, to encode
independently-shot feature films, or to generate local advertising for
your cinema.
</para>

</section>
</chapter>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Installation</title>

<section>
<title>Windows</title>

<para>
To install DVD-o-matic on Windows, simply download the installer from
<ulink url="http://carlh.net/software/dvdomatic">http://carlh.net</ulink>
and double-click it.  Click through the installer wizard, and
DVD-o-matic will be installed to your machine.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Linux</title>

<para>
Installation on Linux is currently a little involved, as there are no
packages available (yet); you will have to compile it from source.
</para>

<para>
The following dependencies are required:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><ulink url="http://ffmpeg.org/">FFmpeg</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.mega-nerd.com/libsndfile/">libsndfile</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.openssl.org/">OpenSSL</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.openjpeg.org/">libopenjpeg</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/script/index.php">ImageMagick</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.boost.org/">Boost</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.libssh.org/">libssh</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.gtk.org/">GTK</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://www.wxwidgets.org/">wxWidgets</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="http://carlh.net/software/libdcp/">libdcp</ulink></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Once you have installed the development packages for the dependencies,
download the source code from <ulink
url="http://carlh.net/software/dvdomatic">http://carlh.net</ulink>,
unpack it and run the following commands from inside the source
directory:
</para>

<programlisting>
./waf configure
./waf build
sudo ./waf install
</programlisting>

<para>
With any luck, this will build and install DVD-o-matic on your system.  To run it, enter:
</para>

<programlisting>
dvdomatic
</programlisting>

<para>
in a shell.
</para>

</section>
</chapter>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Creating a video DCP with DVD-o-matic</title>

<para>
In this chapter we will see how to create a video DCP using DVD-o-matic.
</para>

<section>
<title>Creating a new film</title>

<para>
Let's make a very simple DCP to see how DVD-o-matic works.  First, we
need some content.  Download the low-resolution trailer for the open
movie <ulink url="http://sintel.org/">Sintel</ulink> from <ulink
url="http://ftp.nluug.nl/ftp/graphics/blender/apricot/trailer/Sintel_Trailer1.480p.DivX_Plus_HD.mkv">their
website</ulink>.  Generally, of course, one would want to use the
highest-resolution material available, but for this test we will use
the low-resolution version to save everyone's bandwidth bills.
</para>

<para>
Now, start DVD-o-matic and its window will open.  First, we will
create a new film.  A &lsquo;film&rsquo; is how DVD-o-matic refers to
a piece of content, along with some settings, which we will make into
a DCP.  DVD-o-matic stores its data in a folder on your disk while it
creates the DCP.  will use to store its working files while it creates
your DCP.  You can create a new film by selecting
<guilabel>New</guilabel> from the <guilabel>File</guilabel> menu, as
shown in <xref linkend="fig-file-new"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-file-new"> 
  <title>Creating a new film</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/file-new&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
This will open a dialogue box for the new film, as shown in <xref
linkend="fig-new-film"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-new-film"> 
  <title>Dialogue box for creating a new film</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/new-film&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
In this dialogue box you can choose a name for the film.  This will be
used to name the folder to store its data in, and also as the initial
name for the DCP itself.  You can also set whereabouts you want to create
the film.  In the example from the figure, DVD-o-matic will create a
folder called &lsquo;DCP Test&rsquo; inside my home folder (carl) into which it
will write its working files.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Selecting content</title>

<para>
The next step is to set the content that you want to use.  Click the
content selector, as shown in <xref
linkend="fig-click-content-selector"/> and the a file chooser will
open for you to select the content file to use, as shown in <xref
linkend="fig-select-content-file"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-click-content-selector">
  <title>Opening the content selector</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/click-content-selector&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<figure id="fig-select-content-file"> 
  <title>Selecting the content file</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/select-content-file&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Select your content file and click <guilabel>Open</guilabel>.  In this
case, we are using the Sintel trailer that we downloaded earlier.
</para>

<para>
When you do this, DVD-o-maticw will take a look at your file.  After a
short while (when the progress bars at the bottom right of the window
have finished), you can look through your content using the slider to
the right of the window, as shown in <xref linkend="fig-examine-thumbs"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-examine-thumbs"> 
  <title>Examining the content</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/examine-thumbs&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Dragging the slider will move through your video.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Setting up</title>

<para>
Now there are a few things to set up to describe how the DCP should be
created, as shown in <xref linkend="fig-setup"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-setup"> 
  <title>Setting up</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/setup&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The first thing is the content type.  This can be
&lsquo;feature&rsquo;, &lsquo;trailer&rsquo; or whatever; select the
required type from the drop-down list.
</para>

<para>
Next is the format.  This will govern the shape that DVD-o-matic will
make your image into.  Select the aspect ratio that your content
should be presented in.  The &lsquo;4:3 within Flat&rsquo; and
&lsquo;16:9 within Flat&rsquo; settings will put the image at the
specified ratio within a Flat (1.85:1) frame, so that you can project
the DCP using your projector's Flat preset.
</para>

<para>
The remaining options can often be left alone, but may sometimes be
useful.  The &lsquo;crop&rsquo; settings can be used to crop your
content, which can be useful to remove black borders from round the
edges of DVD images, for example.  The <guilabel>L</guilabel>,
<guilabel>R</guilabel>, <guilabel>T</guilabel> and
<guilabel>B</guilabel> settings correspond to the left, right, top and
bottom of the image respectively.  The specified number of pixels will
be trimmed from each edge, and your content image in the right of the
window will be updated to show the cropping in action.
</para>

<para>
The &lsquo;filters&rsquo; settings allow you to apply various video
filters to the image.  These may be useful to try to improve
poor-quality sources like DVDs.  We will discuss filtering later in the manual.
<!-- XXX: link -->
</para>

<para>
The &lsquo;scaler&rsquo; is the method that will be used to scale up
your content to the required size for the DCP, if required.  We will
discuss the options in more detail later; Bicubic is a fine choice in
most situations.
<!-- XXX: link -->
</para>

<para>
&lsquo;Audio Gain&rsquo; is used to alter the volume of the
soundtrack.  The specified gain (in dB) will be applied to each sound
channel before it is written to the DCP.
</para>

<para>
&lsquo;Audio Delay&rsquo; is used to adjust the synchronisation
between audio and video.  A positive delay will move the audio later
with respect to the video, and a negative delay will move it earlier.
</para>

<!-- XXX: I don't think FPS should be editable -->

<!-- XXX: Range -->

</section>

</chapter>

</book>
